# Gordon A. Pratt, P. Eng.

11 Briarwood Avenue, Mississauga, Ontario, L5G 3N4

gordon@prattaero.com

ca.linkedin.com/in/gordonapratt

### **Profile**

Senior Business Leader with extensive experience in the management of technical products

Experienced with all functions and phases of the product value chain and life cycle.

Track record of value creation through the integration of technical solutions with business and market requirements and customer needs.

Effective team leadership, cross-functional integration and engagement.

## Skills, Experience, Competencies

- Portfolio management, engineering development and product change management
- Program management, decision making, risk management and governance
- Strategic planning, competitive benchmarking and market positioning
- Price and revenue modeling, margin management and financial business case evaluation
- Sales and Contracts processes, brand management, communications and media relations
- Vendor evaluation, acquisition and supplier management
- Customer support, in-service product performance and warranty management
- Cross-functional leadership, team leadership, coaching, mentoring
- Execution, evaluation, problem solving and improvement

## **Career Experience**

## Principal Consultant at Pratt Aero Consulting Inc.

(February 2015 to present)

Providing consulting services in Engineering Management, Program Management and Strategic Planning to aircraft manufacturers, industry suppliers and manufactures of complex technical products.

#### **Bombardier Aerospace**

1982 - 2014

A world leader in the design and manufacturing of innovative aviation products and services for business, commercial and amphibious aircraft markets.

#### Director, O400 Program Management and Strategy

(October 2013 to October 2014)

Program and Product leadership, accountable for the value contribution of the Q400 Regional Turboprop aircraft program within Bombardier's product portfolio and to improve the product's competitiveness in the regional airline market globally. Responsible for leading the contributions of all functional departments into an integrated program strategy.

Focused on improving the clarity and effectiveness of the program business plan. Utilized modeling to evaluate the impact of pricing, unit costs, production rates and market share, etc. on financial results and program performance. Generated one-year and five-year executable plans, backed-up by a robust business-case evaluation, implementation and governance process, reviewed and updated as part of the yearly strategic business cycle.

#### **Director, Q400 Program Management**

(2004 to 2013)

Accountable for managing cross-function activities to achieve program and product goals via planning of program objectives & priorities, work statement & budgeting and change management, utilizing strong project management and governance processes. Oversaw significant program growth and complexity as the customer base for the product increased from 10 airlines initially to over 50 airlines and aircraft in-service increased from 40 to over 400 units.

#### **Director, Engineering Product Development**

(1998 to 2004)

Leader of the Engineering Product Development team in support of Bombardier's regional turboprop aircraft programs.

Worked extensively with airline leaders and suppliers to facilitate the entry-into-service of a new aircraft with an emphasis on problem-solving to increase in-service performance and reliability to mature levels. Led the development and fielding of solutions, many projects running concurrently with budgets in \$millions, cycles exceeding one year. Subsequently negotiated the resolution of the associated commercial issues with both customers and suppliers.

#### Engineering Manager, Learjet M45 Wing Design

(1992 to 1998)

A member of the Program Leadership team with partner companies in the US and UK responsible to meet cost, schedule and technical design objectives in bringing an all-new business jet to market.

Led the Engineering team of over 120 people tasked with the designing a business jet wing from start of design to aircraft certification and entry-into-service. Successfully led the deployment of crossfunctional design/manufacturing teams using computer modeling as the enabling technology to meet design goals and shorten the development cycle.

#### Engineering Specialist, de Havilland/Boeing Canada

(1982 to 1992)

Held several roles within the Engineering department that consolidated formal education with practical experience and developed the ability to be effective in a large matrix organization working on complex technical products in a highly regulated industry.

Trained by Boeing as a team leader and facilitator and selected to facilitate the Executive Quality Improvement Team, developing enhanced skills in leading teams and engaging people.

### **Education and Affiliations**

- B.Sc. (Honours) Mechanical Engineering, Queen's University at Kingston, Ontario
- Member, Professional Engineers Ontario

## **Personal Notes and Interests**

- Past-President of the DeHavilland Flying Club
- Private Pilot's License
- Former leader of Cubs and Beavers
- Camping, canoeing
- Mountain biking and road biking
- Woodworking and renovations